Sito della traduzione: http://trionfo.gelma.net
Ciao, sono Bob Cringely e voglio narrarvi l'incredibile storia
della conquista del mondo dei personal computer.
Perché ve lo sto raccontando da una partita di basket? Bhe, mi
piace questo sport, ma soprattutto per quel tipo laggiù.
Si tratta di Paul Allen e tutto ciò che vedete è suo: la squadra
di basket, lo stadio,
perfino le ballerine.
Grazie ai personal computer ha guadagnato 8 miliardi di dollari da
spendere in questi giocattoli.
Vent'anni fa (1976) Allen e un compagno di liceo, Bill Gates,
gestivano da soli un'azienda di software chiamata Microsoft.
Oggi Allen è più ricco di Dio, e Gates è più ricco di Allen.
Vent'anni fa, giovani come Paul Allen e Bill Gates
inventarono il personal computer
iniziando una rivoluzione che ha cambiato il modo in cui
viviamo, lavoriamo e comunichiamo.
Sembra incredibile che vent'anni fa non esistessero
i personal computer,
ora si tratta della terza industria nel mondo,
posizionata tra la produzione di energia e il narcotraffico
ma la cosa più stupefacente è che il tutto è iniziato casualmente
quando un manipolo di (gelma) disenfranchised nerd voleva impressionare gli amici.
Questa è la storia di come un pugno di amici abbia dato vita a
una rivoluzione industriale.
Come abbiano cambiato la cultura degli affari, di come abbiano fatto storia.
Sono stato estremamente fortunato nel trovarmi nel posto giusto in Silicon Valley,
nel momento storico giusto quando questa invenzione ha visto la luce.
Nessuno di noi due credeva sarebbe durata a lungo,
lo facevamo solo per divertimento
e anche se probabilmente ci avessimo perso del danaro
avremmo potuto dire di aver avuto una nostra azienda.
Tutti noi volevamo semplicemente stare insieme, sperando
di aver visto giusto sull'esplosione del fenomeno PC.
Mi fermo e dico: "Wow! Il PC è diventato parte integrante del
modo di vivere
Gelma and we certainly surged with it. I used to stop and say
hmmm pretty incredible ride.
Molte di queste persone provengono da ciò che io chiamo casa.
La Silicon Valley, a sud di San Francisco, in California.
Nati vicino alle aziende elettroniche
che hanno dato il nome a questo posto
i pionieri della rivoluzione dei PC provenivano, principalmente,
dalla classe media bianca della tranquilla periferia.
Ma non sono le loro case che ci interessano, bensì i loro garage.
Questo è il mio garage e questa è tutto il mio ciarpame.
Probabilmente sono uno dei pochi nella Silicon Valley
ad avere spazio in garage per l'auto, pare che la
maggioranza sia più propensa a sfruttarli per farci
soldi e aziende informatiche,
ma io non ho fatto fortuna. Sono un fallito. Ho scritto
programmi più o meno funzionanti, costruito e progettato
periferiche che, onestamente, non hanno mai funzionato.
Ma questo fa di me la persona ideale per raccontare la genesi del
mondo dei PC. Ne sono il principale pettegolo, perché tutti mi confidano
i proprî segreti.
Questa è casa mia, dove scrivo editoriali di gossip per una
rivista di informatica.
Perdonate la confusione.
Realtà in costante evoluzione come l'industria dei PC sono
dominate da dicerie e pettegolezzi. Mi nutro di entrambi.
La mia mail è piena di informazioni riservate che spaziano
dai difetti dei prodotti fino ai nomi degli amanti.
Ciò che unisce questi pettegoli è il desiderio di conoscere la verità.
Queste persone, e la loro passione per la tecnologia, hanno
alimentato la rivoluzione del PC.
Capirli significa capirne la rivoluzione.
Andiamo a incontrarne alcuni.
Incontriamo Edwin Chin una sabato mattino al Magazzino della Roba Stramba.
Potrebbe essere il 1976 o il 1996 perché c'è sempre una nuova
generazione di smanettoni come Edwin
interessati. Molti dei suoi coetanei staranno guardando la TV,
ma non Edwin.
Mi sono appassionato all'elettronica e alla tecnologia
fin dai 6-7 anni.
Quandi anni hai ora, Edwin?
- Dieci.
Non è un caso che l'unica donna nelle vicinanze sia annoiata,
perché questa è roba da uomini, l'ossessione di un particolare tipo
di uomini che preferiscono lottare con una scatola elettronica che
con un modo di persone imprevedibili.
Sono ingegneri, programmatori, hackers, techies,
ma soprattutto nerds.
Direi che un nerd sia una persona che usa un telefono
per parlare con altri di telefoni.
Quindi un computer nerd è qualcuno che usa
un computer al solo scopo di farlo.
Le persone hanno differenti tipi e livelli di passioni.
Alcuni sono appassionati di database, percepiscono la normalizzazione
come il nirvana, sono interessati solo a questo,
è ciò che li fa alzare al mattino.
Cosa pensano i tuoi amici di te?
Amico, è un nerd.
Ma non mi importa. Sono abituato a sentirmi chiamato nerd.
Non si può lasciare che altri distruggano i nostri sogni.
Nella Silicon Valley il sogno è di crescere per diventare uno
come...
Graham Spencer is chief programmer for Architext Software
six guys who graduated from Stanford University and started
a company just because they like each other.
This is a modern-day startup, but at heart it's no different from
PC pioneers like Apple, or Microsoft,
nerds who share a dream.
Their hobby is their business
and the culture they've created is identical to that of a
thousand other technology companies.
First, they dumped the idea of nine to five. In this industry,
you can work any 80 hours per week you like.
...my cap which I use to cover my eyes and sleep in
the early morning while everybody is coming in.
We didn't even obey a 24 hour clock, we'd come in and
programme for a couple of days straight.
We'd - you know, four or five of us, when it was time to eat
we'd all get in our cars, kind of race over to the restaurant
and sit and talk about what we were doing, sometimes I'd get...
...excited talking about things, I'd forget to eat,
but then you know, we'd just go back
and programme some more. It was us and our friends -
those were fun days.
Let's look in the refrigerator... Woah! We have
coke and cold pizza.
I drink about two litres of coke a day.
Two litres of coke a day and do you like think of it as brain food?
It keeps me going you know, that and listening to heavy metal,
and get caffeinated and hack.
I'd sit down in my room on the floor with sheets of paper spread
all around with my computer design I was working on.
And always I noticed that I was up pretty late at night and I had
lots of cokes - it's just part of that life.
A combination of stale pizza and body odour and spilt cola
kinda ground in to the rug.
I brought some spaghetti to work and then forgot to wash out the
container for the last couple of days, maybe six or seven...
if I had to be honest. Ooh, that smells bad.
Eating, bathing, having a girlfriend, having an active social life
is incidental, it gets in the way of code time. Writing code
is the primary force that drives our lives so
anything that interrupts that is is wasteful.
What is it about the internal logic of a computer
that's so enticing?
For one thing, such logic CAN be understood,
as opposed to things that can't be understood at all,
like the motivations of young women, say,
or of the French.
Let me explain...
Time for the Cringely crash course in basic computers,
Part 1.
This is a mainframe computer,
all of these cabinets are one machine. In the old days
all computers were this size
they were tended by engineers in white coats
a kind of priesthood who took their jobs very seriously.
Now all computers work pretty much the same, whether
it's a giant that serves two thousand users like this one,
or a little notebook that serves only me.
They process numerical data - adding, multiplying,
comparing,
the fact is if you can quantify it a computer can handle it.
It's the emotional stuff they don't know what to do with.
The data must be put into a special binary code
consisting only of ones and zeros.
And you have to give the computer instructions, also
in code, to tell it exactly what to do wth the data
and in what order. These instructions are called a program.
In the early days, you put in the instructions by
flipping switches or loaded them from paper tape.
This was called machine language.
It made computers a pain to use.
Even worse, every type of computer spoke a different
machine language.
The ENIAC could compute the thirty second trajectory
of a shell in twenty seconds.
Operators required two days to program it do so.
Then a US Navy captain named Grace Hopper
solved the problem.
She invented a computer language, English words that
the computer itself could translate into binary code.
Now users could type whole lists of instructions
into a computer
rather than flipping those damned switches.
Like most things having to do with computers,
that first language had a silly name - COBOL.
It was followed by other languages like FORTRAN and BASIC
and they all made computing just a bit more user-friendly.
So when some nerd tells you he's been up all night
programming or writing software or hacking code,
what he really means is he's been typing long lists of
instructions into his computer.
Mainframe computers were far from personal. They sat
in big air-conditioned rooms
at insurance companies, phone companies, and the bank,
and their main function was to get us confused with
some other guy named Cringely,
who was a deadbeat and had a criminal record.
Eventually computer terminals did begin to
appear in some schools,
but most of us paid no attention.
But there was usually one kid who did pay attention,
falling in love with the digital purity of those ones and zeros.
He was the nerd.
And I took this book home that described the PDP 8 computer
and it just...oh, it was just like a bible to me.
I mean, all these things that for some reason I'd fallen
in love with, like you might fall in love with...
a card game called Magic, or you might fall in love with doing
crossword puzzles or something else,
or playing a musical instrument, I fell in love with these
little descriptions of computers on their insides,
and it was a little mathematics, I could work out some
problems on paper and solve it and see how it's done,
and I could come up with my own solutions
and feel good inside.
So you would keyboard these commands in and then you
would wait for a while and then the thing would go dadadada...
and it would tell you something out,
but even with that it was still remarkable - especially for
a ten year old,
that you could write a programme in Basic let's say or Fortran
and actually this machine would sort of take your idea
and it would sort of execute your idea and
give you back some results
and if they were the results that you predicted your program
really worked it was an incredibly thrilling experience.
Nerds wanted their own computers right from the beginning,
but it took a technological breakthrough to make that possible.
This is it, the chip, the microprocessor, this is what allows you
to have a mainframe computer on your desk.
In the 1950s mainframes were as big as this garage and that's
because they were filled with thousands of these,
vacuum tubes or valves.
Eventually the valves were made much smaller and
replaced with transistors,
still too big however to make a computer that could fit
on your desk.
What that took was further miniaturisation. Here we have a single
piece of silicon etched with thousands of transistors.
This microprocessor holds more than a million transistors and
that's the secret of the personal computer
and that's why they call it silicon valley not computer valley.
These are the people who invented the microprocessor -- Intel.
Intel was started 28 years ago by a handful of guys after a row
with their old boss.
Their microprocessors today power 85 percent
of the world's computers.
Intel not only invented the chip, they are responsible for the
laid-back Silicon Valley working style.
Everyone was on a first-name basis.
There were no reserved parking places, no offices, only cubicles.
It's still true today. Here's the chairman's cubicle.
Knock, knock I knocked at the door but there's no door.
Gordon Moore is one of the Intel founders worth $3 billion.
With money like that, I'd have a door.
In a business like this the people with the power are the ones
that have the understanding of what's going on,
not necessarily the ones on top.
And it's very important that those people that have the knowledge
are the ones that make the decisions.
So we set up something where everyone who had the knowledge
had an equal say in what was going on.
Intel's microprocessors kept getting more powerful.
They soon had enough horsepower to run a whole computer.
Only Intel didn't appreciate the brilliance of their own product,
seeing it as useful mainly for powering calculators
or traffic lights.
Intel had all the elements necessary to invent the PC business,
but they just didn't get it.
Lucky for us, someone did.
This is the chip that launched the personal computer revolution.
This is the magazine that announced it.
In January 1975 featured on the cover was the world's first
personal computer the Altair 8800.
It was the crazy idea of an ex-airforce officer from Georgia:
Ed Roberts.
If you look at it you know it was kind of grandiose
almost megalomaniac kind of scheme you know
and right now I couldn't do it because I could see right off
there's no way you could do this.
But at that time you know we just lacked the eh the benefits
of age and experience.
We didn't know we couldn't do it.
20 years after Ed Roberts' flash of brilliance, this exhibit is being
held to celebrate the anniversary of the Altair.
Like every other PC pioneer, Ed built his computer just because
he wanted one to play with.
There were some of us that lusted after computers
really at that time.
All the computers in the world tended to be in big centres
and you had to get permission to get close to them, and you know,
nobody had access to computers.
And the idea that you could have your own computer and do
whatever you wanted to with it,
whenever you wanted to, was fantastic.
And where was this all happening? It was far from Silicon Valley,
Intel, or IBM.
Out in the desert near the airport in Albuquerque, New Mexico,
Ed Roberts ran a calculator company called MITS.
Having an ugly building wasn't it's only problem:
MITS was going bankrupt.
Nobody was buying calculators and Ed needed $65,000
just to stay afloat.
And we went to the bank, we had a late night meeting,
and the issue was whether we closed MITS down or they loaned us
an additional sixty-five thousand
and I was asked how many machines that I think we would sell
in the next year after it was introduced,
and I said eight hundred, which was considered
a wild-eyed optimist at that.
Within a month after it was introduced we were getting
two hundred and fifty orders a day.
The Altair wasn't even a computer, it was a computer KIT.
- Wow this is a pretty well equipped machine.
You had to build it yourself and even then it usually didn't work.
Still, the demand was amazing.
There were actually people that came to MITS, a couple of people
with camper trailers
and camped out inthe parking lot waiting for their machines.
I mean, they were so eager.
I mean I think everybody had sort of daydream,
Ed Walter Mitteyed about owning a computer.
The surprise was that it would be possible for the
average college student, for example,
who was living on bare subsistence, to actually buy a computer.
This is what really amazed me was that people were so,
there was a sort of pent up demand
for having your own computer.
And if it could be that cheap what a wonderful thing.
This is an Altair computer - the first personal computer.
And not just any Altair - this is Altair serial number 2,
the second one made.
The first Altair made was sent off to be photographed
at a magazine and was lost in the mail.
So this is the oldest personal computer in the world.
Pretty historic junk but the question is what do you do with it?
I mean it has a front panel with switches that you can click
back and forth and some lights
but in the back there's no place to connect a keyboard, there's no
place to connect a monitor, there's no place to connect a printer,
in fact there practically nothing at all that you can really do
with this thing
but back then 1975, the people who had it were thrilled.
The nerds formed clubs to talk about their new toy.
One of the first was the Homebrew Computer Club, which met on
Wednesday evenings in a hall rented from Stanford University
in Silicon Valley.
Presiding over near-anarchy was Lee Felsenstein who pretended
to be in charge.
And I would start the meeting by making a horrendous loud noise
because everyone was talking and I had to get some attention somehow.
And I would use it to call upon the person in question.
I'd make threatening gestures with it.
Most of us were in the electronics industry to a certain extent,
there was also a stratem of physicians
and there were a lot radio amateurs for instance finding a new
technology that wasn't stale.
But most of us were at a sort of middle level or downwards.
We saw ourselves as crazed ignored geniuses or possibly geniuses
but at least we could each hope to get our hands on a computer
of our own.
The very uselessness of the Altair is what drove the hobbyists together.
Roger Melen and Harry Garland started an early computer company.
They came here to meet others and to figure out just what the heck
could be done with this new toy
a solution in search of a problem.
The Altair was tedious to use.
At first, the only way that data and instructions could be given
to the computer, was by flipping switches.
Take something trivial like 2+2.
Each 2 needed eight different switches to be flipped, then a ninth
switch was used to load them all.
'And' required another nine switches. The answer 4 was if the third
light from the left turned on. Eureka!
So if you had a program that was a hundred bytes long you had
to go this procedure a hundred times to load that in the memory.
- It took a long time.
And what happened if you lost power or if you lost
your way in the middle?
You cried.
The Altair may have been frustrating, but it drove the nerds
to experiment,
finding real uses for the useless box, turning it from a curiosity
to a computer.
Steve Dumpier set up an Altair, ehm laboriously keyed a program
into it.
Somebody knocked a plug out of the wall and he had to do that
all over again but nobody knew what this was about.
After all, was it just going to sit and flash its lights? No.
You put a little eh transistor radio next to the Altair
and he would by manipulating the length of loops in the sofware,
could play tunes.
The radio began playing 'Fool on the Hill'....Da da da, da da da....
and the tinny little tunes that you could tell were coming from the
noise that the computer was generated being picked up by the radio.
Everybody rose and applauded.
I proposed that he receive the stripped Philips Screw Award for
finding a use for something previously thought useless.
But I think everybody was too busy applauding to even hear me.
It was a very exciting thing, it was probably the first thing
the Altair actually did.
Turning the Altair into a useful tool required a programming language
so users could type their programs in rather than flipping switches.
What it needed was a version of some big computer language
like BASIC, only modified for the PC.
This was called a BASIC interpreter, but it didn't yet exist because
the experts all thought
that not even BASIC was basic enough to fit inside the tiny
Altair memory.
Yet again the experts were wrong.
Here comes the guy who solved the problem.
Twenty years after finishing the first microcomputer BASIC,
Paul Allen is returning to Albuquerque for a celebration of that event,
this time with his $15 million jet and three foot red carpet.
At a time when I was killing brain cells, this guy was founding
an empire.
He has come to eat rubber chicken in honor of the Altair's
20th anniversary.
I'd like to introduce to you - Paul Allen.
Allen co-founded Microsoft with his younger buddy from high school,
Bill Gates.
One day in Boston, I was in Harvard Square I saw a cover of
Popular Electronics with this thing that looked like
what I had been imagining, and so I grabbed it off the shelf,
I looked at it and I bought it and
I ran back to Bill's dorm, and I think he was probably playing poker
that night and usually losing money at that point.
One of the few times when that's been the case.
Paul showed that to me and then okay, here was a company
that would be needing software.
And he said OK we gotta call these guys up and see if this thing's
for real.
We realised that things were starting to happen, and just because
we'd had a vision for a long time of where this chip could go,
what it could mean er,
that didn't mean the industry was going to wait for us while I stayed
and - and finished my Degree at Harvard.
So called up Ed you know, we told him we've got this Basic and
it's you know just for your machine, and it's, you know,
not that far from being done, and we'd like to come
out and show it to you.
So we created this BASIC interpreter. Paul took the paper tape er, and
and flew out. In fact, the night before, he - he got some sleep while
I double checked everything to make sure
that we had er, had it all right.
But I had no idea what it was really going to be like to try to
run the software.
It had never been run on an actual computer before.
He was very nervous about whether this would actually work.
And then he got to the office and we all gathered around him
and he put his fingers on the switches
and he loaded BASIC with paper tape into the Altair.
I was just I was so nervous....this is just....it's not going to work
and it worked.
And it came up, and it could do a few little simple things.
And it was amazing when Paul called me up and said the thing
had worked the first time.
And of course, it was incredibly fast.
And it printed out memory size and I think Bill said
"it printed something!". So I said yeah, yeah.
Oh, that was - that was unbelievable. The fact that it really worked
er, was - was - was a breakthrough.
Maybe there wouldn't be a Microsoft if the screen hadn't come alive,
who knows, it might all be quite different.
After the demo succeeded, Bill forgot about finishing university.
Afraid of missing his chance to dominate the new industry,
he joined Allen in what was then the the center of world
microcomputing research
among the sleezy bars and gas stations of Albuquerque, New Mexico.
And they lived across the street from MITS in the Sundowner Motel,
and the prostitutes and the drug dealers out on the corner,
and they were writing BASIC for the Altair computer, and gradually
they actually started Microsoft here in Albuquerque.
We hired some of our high school friends basically to come down and
eh stay with us in our apartment, which became very crowded.
We were pretty young. We started when I was 19 and so we just had
a lot of - a lot of energy.
They worked really hard. They listened to really loud music,
I could hardly stand to go to the software room sometimes
because the music would be banging off the walls, mostly acid rock.
You know we'd usually go out, eat pizzas and then go out and watch
action movies.
They would work all night long, and there were days when Bill Gates
would be sleeping on the floor in the software lab.
Sometimes it would be Bill and these two other guys all,
you know, sitting on tables around the apartment
with stacks and stacks of paper writing, converting the BASIC
for the 8080.
I still know the source code by heart, and that was er, er,
a work of love, you know, we just kept tuning and tuning that thing.
And - and so that kind of craftsmanship paid off.
BASIC let the Altair be used for both fun stuff and real work.
People attached terminals to the computer and began writing games,
word processors, and accounting programs.
Most of us didn't notice but soon there was thriving industry
for enthusiasts.
By the end of 1975, dozens of other companies
were building microcomputers.
We created an industry and I think that goes completely unnoticed.
I mean there was nothing - every aspect of the industry when you talk
about software, hardware, application stuff,
dealerships, you name it, it was all in a mess.
It was a wild time. It was a very exciting time.
and the first user convention - where we got people to come in and
tell us what they were doing, what they were excited about,
and other companies like Processor Technology or Imsai or Comemco
got going as add-on companies.
These companies are long-forgotten, but they were the -
the humble beginnings of the - of the PC industry.
Left in the hands of those early hobbyists the PC might never have
made it to the shopping mall.
Reaching the wider market required a different type of vision.
Enter the flower children of California, who thought the PC was,
well, groovy.
Remember that the Sixties happened in the early Seventies, right,
so you have to remember that and that's sort of when I came of age.
So I saw a lot of this and to me the spark of that
was that there was something beyond sort of what you see every day.
It's the same thing that causes people to want to be
poets instead of bankers.
And I think that's a wonderful thing. And I think that that same spirit
can be put into products,
and those products can be manufactured and given to people
and they can sense that spirit.
To help you understand all this, I will now take off my clothes.
- And he says well frame relay is scaleable.
Jim Warren knows better than most what the hippy movement
did for the PC.
A sixties radical himself, he staged the West Coast Computer Faire
for a time the biggest computer show in the world.
The Faire was where the PC really arrived. It's also where Jim got rich.
- So eh Jim is this where you hold all your meetings?
- Uhm as many as possible - sure why not.
- This is how silicon vallye entrepreneurs conduct business?
Believe it or not, Jim once taught mathematics at a
Catholic girls school.
Jim was immediately fascinated by the PC like many Bay Area hippies.
The California counter culture was crucial to the PC's development.
And the whole spirit there was working together, was sharing.
You shared your dope, you shared your bed, you shared your life,
you shared your hopes.
And a whole bunch of us had the same community spirit
and that permeated the whole Home Brew Computer Club.
As soon as somebody would solve a problem they'd come running
down to the Home Brew Computer Club's next meeting and say:
hey everybody you know that problem that all of us
have been trying to figure out how to solve,
here's the solution, isn't this wonderful?
Aren't I a great guy?
And it's my contention that that is a major component of why
Silicon Valley was able to
develop the technology as rapidly as it did,
because we were all sharing - everybody won!
Out of this creative show-and-tell came Apple Computer,
the first mass market PC company.
The Apple founders, a couple of recent graduates from
Homestead High were regulars at Homebrew meetings.
Steve Wozniak was the technical wizard
and Steve Jobs was the visionary who saw microcomputers
as a possible business.
The first Apple computer was primitive.
It was cobbled together by Woz to impress his friends
at the Hombrew meetings.
Everybody was interested in computers so I started getting
a crowd around me
because even although I was too shy to raise my hand
and say anything in a club meeting
after the club meetings I would put my computer that I had built and
every week it had a little bit more working on it too
but I would set it down and let people type on the keyboard
and I would explain what's in it
If they would come up to me and ask the question I can answer
eh you know nowadays I would have the ability to tell them what it is
you know and be a little bit more promotional
but back then I could only answer questions that they asked me
but a kinda group started gathering around me.
And Steve Jobs saw that I had a lot of interest around me at the club
and he said "let's start selling it"
and let's make this company. He came up with the name Apple
and eh and eh that's how it started.
Apple was at best a funky company...started by a couple of
teenage hackers who
had previously been working as Alice in Wonderland characters in a
local shopping mall and they started it in this garage right here.
The first Apple computer was built here, now there are more than
ten million in use around the world.
And I was there - well for a short time I was an employee of
Apple Computer,
employee number 12 and one day I helped move materials
out of this garage.
At the time Steve Jobs said that the company was short of loot
so he offered to pay me in company shares,
but I held out for the money -
my mother still reminds me of that incident.
The Apple 1 was even less of a computer than the Altair
a single circuit board that came with neither a case nor a keyboard.
Still, Steve Jobs managed to sell 50 Apple 1's.
That experience showed Jobs there was a market for a real computer:
the Apple II.
It was very clear to me that while there were a bunch of
hardware hobbyists
that could assemble their own computers, or at least take our board
and add the transformers for the power supply and the case
the keyboard and go get, you know, et cetera,
go get the rest of the stuff.
For every one of those there were a thousand people that couldn't
do that, but wanted to mess around with programming
software hobbyists. Just like I had been when I was, you know, ten,
discovering that computer.
And so my dream for the Apple 2 was to sell the first real
packaged computer.
Steve Jobs's dream was impossible.
It needed too many chips, making the product too complicated
and expensive to build.
But Woz didn't know it was impossible.
And then I got in to a way of why have memory for your TV screen
and memory for your computer, make them one,
and that shrunk the chips down, and I shrunk the chips here,
and why not take all these timing circuits
and I looked through manuals and found a chip that did it in one
chip instead of five, and reduced that,
and one thing after another after another happened.
I wound up with so few chips, when I was done I said:
hey, a computer that you could program to generate
coloured patterns on a screen,
or data or words or play games or anything,
it was just the computer I wanted, you know, for myself pretty much,
but it had turned out so good.
He said: "I think we have a computer we could sell a thousand
a month of."
How can you sell a thousand a month, you know?
But we needed some money for tooling the case, things like that,
we needed a few hundred thousand dollars.
That was a lot of money for two people who had nothing in their lives
to speak of, didn't have a 400 dollar bank account.
So I went looking for some venture capital.
The scruffy 19 year-old seduced the conservative world
of venture capitalists.
The man Jobs persuaded to part with his cash was Arthur Rock,
the inventor of venture capital and the man who had
originally funded Intel.
At least the Intel boys had graduated from university
and owned suits.
Well, he wore sandals and he had long, very long hair and
a beard and a moustache,
but very articulate.
He was, I think at one time in his life, and it was probably when
I first met him that he ate nothing but fruit.
- So as a mainline venture capitalist, is this...
- This is not the norm.
With money in hand and under occasional adult supervision from
an ex-Intel manager named Mike Markkula,
Woz & Jobs finished the Apple II and ordered a local factory
to build 1000 machines.
Two years passed between the Altair and the Apple 2.
And in that time a lot of things changed.
We went from a computer that was designed for hobbyists and
engineers and certainly looked like a piece of test equipment
to a computer that looked like a piece of consumer electronics
and we can thank Steve Jobs for that - his sense of design
demanded that this structural foam case be used for the Apple 2
the first case of its type on a personal computer.
And not that there wasn't good engineering inside either.
The Apple 2 was a model of efficient engineering,
here's the floppy disk drive controller for example. There are eight chips
here where previously there would have been thirty-five.
This is an amazing bit of engineering that we can attribute to
Steve Wozniak
who is certainly the Mozart of digital design and all told it turned
the Apple 2 into a sensation.
The Apple II was launched at Jim Warren's West Coast Computer Faire,
one of the first big microcomputer shows.
The 1978 show drew thousands of attendees and dozens of exhibitors
many of them members of the Homebrew Computer Club,
which spawned most of the early microcomputer companies.
But there was only one company showing something
that looked like a modern personal computer.
Right by the entrance, in a prime spot negotiated by Steve Jobs,
sat the Apple II.
It mesmerized all who saw it.
My recollection is we stole the show,
and a lot of dealers and distributors started lining up and we were off
and running.
- How old were you?
Twenty-one.
Following the West Coast Computer Faire, the next two years were
ones of explosive growth for Apple,
with thousands of customers literally arriving on the doorstep
of the tiny office in Cupertino, California.
Sales and profits grew so quickly that Apple had more money than
the company could spend.
And the company was very young.
The founders were in their twenties and some employees were
even younger, like 14 year-old Chris Espinosa, who never left.
He still works at Apple, almost 20 years later.
And there would be public demonstrations of our product every
Tuesday and Thursday afternoon at 3 o'clock
and that was good because it was after school.
So I would get out of my, you know sophomore-junior year
of high school,
I would ride my little moped down to the Apple offices and at 3 oÍclock
I'd give the demonstrations of the Apple 2.
When we were in the office it was hey jokes and we were wiring up
people's phones to do weird things,
ust every one of us I mean there wasn't a person in Apple I don't think
for a couple of years that was you know super serious.
We were lucky, we had like the hot product of its day.
And some of the people that I did original demos to came up to me
years later and said:
"you know I founded a hundred million dollar chain of computer stores"
based on the demo you showed me one Tuesday afternoon at Apple.
It was really fun.
It went so successful that all of a sudden Steve and I wouldn't have to
worry about work for the rest of our lives.
And then it got even more successful and more successful after that,
and eh it was sort of a shock.
The Apple II set a new standard for personal computers
and showed there was some real money to be made.
Rival companies popped-up all over, but the market was still hobbyists
guys with big beards who thought a good use for their computer was
controlling a model train set.
But for microcomputers to be taken seriously, they had to start
doing things that needed doing,
functions that were useful, not just for fun.
The enthusiast had its limits. To reach the rest of us the Apple 2
needed what nerds call a killer application.
Software that's so useful that people will buy computers just to run it.
For the Apple II, this application was called VisiCalc.
It came straight from the blackboards of the Harvard Business school.
Invented by a graduate student, Dan Bricklin with his programmer friend
Bob Frankston,
VisiCalc was the first electronic spreadsheet.
A spreadsheet is a tool for financial planning,
bringing together for the first time the seduction of money
with the power of microcomputing.
Dan Bricklin's professor at Harvard
showed how companies used a grid of numbers on a blackboard
to work out profits and expenses.
- Sixty down here and your profit would be this minus this which
gives you forty.
- And then well let's see what's the sales growth, say there's a
ten percent...
The trick to a spreadsheet is that all the values in the table
are related to the others.
So changes in one year would ripple through the table,
affecting prices and profits in subseqent years.
Students were asked to calculate how future profits would be affected
by various business scenarios.
It was called running the numbers and they did it laborously by hand.
- Well let's say your initial costs have a hundred fixed costs at the beginning
so now you have a minus twenty
- is how much you make the first year and in the second year you have
a hundred but your variable is say
- let's say twenty-five so now your losing, what is it, it's a pain in the neck
I wasn't very good at this stuff,
- eightyfive
- no no no - fifteen - minus fifteen right and eventually your making money,
- what year do we make money and how much does the cost of money
that's what running numbers was...
Because each value was linked to others, one mistake
could mean disaster.
- ...it blows your all number afterwards because you make all your
calculations based on the other numbers before them.
Dan, who had worked as a programmer,
started daydreaming about how he could use a computer
to replace the tedious hand calculations.
- I imagined that there was this magic blackboard that did like
word processing does word wrapping
- if you make a change to a word it automatically pulls everything back,
well why no recalculate in the same way?
- So that if I change my number, you know, I should have used ten per cent
instead of twelve per cent,
- I could just put it in and it would recalculate everything
and go through it you know
- and that would be this idea of an electronic spread sheet.
Following a model that's common today, Dan Bricklin designed
the program,
but got his friend Bob Frankston to write the actual computer code.
After months of programming late at night when computer time
was cheaper,
the Harvard Business School blackboard came to life.
- Now we've set this up, OK. Then we type a new value in, then
I'm going to take that one hundred,
- I'm going to change it right and here, it recalculated! Woa!
That saved me so much time!
People who saw it and went and got it like an accountant,
I remember showing it
- to one around here and he started shaking and said:
"that's what I do all week, I could do it in an hour you know,"
- you know, they would take their credit cards and shove them
in your face.
I meet these people now they come up to me and say
"I gotta tell you you know..."
(BOB): You changed my life.
(DAN): You changed my life. You made accounting fun and...
- You have to remember what it was like in those days we did not use
the word spreadsheet
- cause nobody knew what a spreadsheet was.
- I came up with the name visible calculator or visicalc because
we wanted to emphasise that aspect.
VisiCalc hit the market in October, 1979, selling for $100.
Marv Goldschmitt sold the first copies from his computer store
in Bedford, Massachusetts.
After a slow start VisiCalc took off.
What it did in our society, it gave people who were obsessed
with numbers,
whether they were in business or at home,
how much am I worth today, what's my stock portfolio worth, how
am I doing against budget on this project.
It gave them an ability to play with scenarios and change it and
say well, what if I do this.
So it put people in a sense in control
of the thing that lots of people in our society feel is driving
them and that's numbers.
The spreadsheet was every businessman's crystal ball.
It answered all those 'what if' questions.
What if I fire the engineering department?
What if I invest $10 million in pantyhose futures?
Look! I'll be rich in under a year and have slimmer thighs
at the same time!
The Computer says so!
The effect of the spreadsheet was enormous.
Armed with an Apple 2 running Visicalc a twenty-four year old MBA
with two pieces of dubious data could convince his
corporate managers
to allow him to loot the corporate pension fund and do a
leverage buy-out.
It was the perfect tool for the eighties...
the lead decade where money was everything and greed was good.
In five years, the PC had gone from a hobbyist's toy
to an engine that shaped the times we lived in.
Thanks to VisiCalc the Apple II made history.
Everybody you talked to just seemed excited about talking
about what we were doing.
And there was this huge media explosion, kind of like the Internet
is receiving today,
of this is the happening thing. You read about it over and over
and over,
and every time you took an airplane flight you read about it,
in every newspaper every week you'd read something
about small computers coming, and Apple was one of the
highlight companies
so we were being portrayed as a leader of a revolution,
and we really felt that we were a leader of a revolution.
We were going to change life a lot.
Pretty good for a company started in a garage three years before.
But not all the PC pioneers made great fortunes. Dan Bricklin decided
not to patent his spreadsheet idea.
Though more than 100 million spreadsheets have been sold
since 1979,
Bricklin and Frankston haven't earned VisiCalc royalties in years.
You know, looking back at how successful a lot of other people
have been it's kind of sad that we weren't as successful...
It would be very nice to be gazillionaires,
but you can also understand that part of the reason was
that that's not what we're trying to be.
We're kids of the Sixties and what did you want to do?
You wanted to make the world better,
and you wanted to make your mark on the world and improve things,
and we did it.
So by the mark of what we would measure ourselves by,
we're very successful.
And what about Ed Roberts?
Three years and 40,000 computers after assembling that first Altair,
the fun was over for Ed.
MITS was just another player in what had become a
competitive market for personal computers.
Roberts sold his company in 1978 and started a new life.
He went back to his native Georgia and retrained as a doctor.
- I hadn't really thought anything at all about it for the last
few years
- until people started taking credit for things that we did at MITS
- eh that's the only thing I think about. It irritates me
- when I think about the things that we did at MITS and we took
all the heat for
- that other people have tried to take credit for
- and that frustrates me.
While Ed Roberts invented the personal computer,
it was the founders of Apple who got rich.
When Apple went public in spectacular fashion in 1980,
Jobs and Woz became multimillionaires.
The nerds had inherited the earth.
I was worth...
...about over a million dollars when I was twenty-three
and over ten million dollars when I was twenty-four,
and over a hundred million dollars when I was twenty-five
and ehm it wasn't that important ehm because I never did it
for the money.
It was just a little hobby company like a lot of people do
not thinking anything of it.
I mean it wasn't as though we both thought it was going to go
a long ways.
It was like we'll both do it for fun
but back then there was a short window in time where one person
who could sit down and do some neat good designs
could turn them into a huge thing like the Apple 2.
It's astonishing that at the beginning of 1975 nobody owned
a personal computer
all there was was a mock-up on a magazine cover
yet within five years there had emerged here in Silicon Valley
a billion dollar industry.
An unhealthy fascination with technology on the part of a few
adolescents
had awakened the nerd within us all.
PC companies were sprouting like mushrooms to meet
the enormous demand.
Apple had emerged as the top fungus and had taken fifty per cent
of the market.
To the boys in Cupertino, every day seemed like Christmas...
but Scrooge was around the corner.
There was a company that everyone associated with the word
'computer',
a company that expected, no demanded to dominate its market:
IBM
Big Blue was on the move
and Silicon Valley would soon be feeling the reverberations.
subtitles by fabiusX
subs@fabiushouse.com
Best watched using Open Subtitles MKV Player